<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Copyright 2001-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Reading Beans (Advanced)</title>
  <author email="jstrachan@apache.org">James Strachan</author>
 </properties>

<body>

    <section name='Interfaces And Abstract Classes'>
        <subsection name='Understanding The Problem'>
            <p>
Betwixt uses the type of the corresponding mapped property to determine the class to be instantiated
when reading xml. But what happens when the type of the mapped property is an interface or
an abstract class and so cannot be instantiated? Well - unless steps are taken to solve this problem,
the read will fail. 
        </p>
            <p>
Betwixt provides a number of different ways to solve this problem. 
One solution is to use <a href='derived.html'>derived beans</a>. This is flexible but means coupling
the xml to a java class structure. Another solution is to use <a href='#Customizing Bean Creation'>custom
bean creation</a> to ensure that an appropriate class is created.
Other solutions follow in this section.
        </p>
    </subsection>
        <subsection name='Specifying An Implementation Class In The Betwixt File'>
            <p>
The class to be instantiated when a (mapped) element is read can be specified via the <code>class</code>
attribute. When present, this should be a fully qualified java class name. A bean of this type
will then be instantiated when the element is read.
        </p>
            <p>
For example, here's a bean:
<source><![CDATA[
package org.apache.commons.betwixt.example;

import java.util.ArrayList;
import java.util.List;

public class ExampleBean {
    
    private String name;
    private List examples = new ArrayList();
    
    public ExampleBean() {}

    public String getName() {
        return name;
    }
    
    public void setName(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }
    
    public List getExamples() {
        return examples;
    }
    
    public void addExample(IExample example) {
        examples.add(example);
    }
}
]]></source>
which contains a List whose contents each implement the <code>IExample</code> interface:
<source><![CDATA[
package org.apache.commons.betwixt.example;

public interface IExample {

    public int getId();
    public void setId(int id);
    public String getName();
    public void setName(String id);
}
]]></source>
Betwixt will create an instance of the following standard implementation:
<source><![CDATA[
package org.apache.commons.betwixt.example;

public class ExampleImpl implements IExample {
    
    private int id;
    private String name;
    
    public ExampleImpl() {}
    
    public int getId() {
        return id;
    }
    public void setId(int id) {
        this.id = id;
    }
    
    public String getName() {
        return name;
    }
    
    public void setName(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }
}
]]></source>
for each <code>example</code> element if the following <code>ExampleBean.betwixt</code> file:

<source><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<info>
    <element name='example-bean'>
        <element name='example' property='examples' class='org.apache.commons.betwixt.example.ExampleImpl'/>
        <addDefaults/>
    </element>
</info>]]></source>
is used.
        </p>        
    </subsection>
</section>

<section name='Reading Beans (Advanced)'>
<subsection name='Adding Custom Digestion Rules'>
    <p>
    Betwixt builds on <code>Apache Digester</code> for bean reading. 
    <code>BeanReader</code> extends <code>Digester</code> 
    and this makes a wide range of functionality available.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    Digester uses <code>Rule</code>'s to specify the xml mapping (for more details see the 
    <a href='http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/digester.html'>Digester documentation</a>).
    Betwixt provides a custom ruleset (<code>BeanRuleSet</code>). This creates <code>Rule</code>'s that
    implement the standard Betwixt mapping for a class. <code>BeanReader.registerBeanClass</code> 
    uses this <code>RuleSet</code> to add these standard betwixt mapping <code>Rule</code>'s
    for the bean class.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    These standard Betwixt mapping rules can be integrated with other Digester <code>Rule</code>'s.
    <code>Rule</code>'s added before <code>registerBeanClass</code> is called will come before (in a 
    Digester sense) the standard betwixt <code>Rule</code>'s. Those added after will come afterwards.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    <strong>Note</strong> that care must be taken with the patterns for additional <code>Rule</code>'s.
    The standard Betwixt mapping will only work if all it's <code>Rule</code>'s are matched.
    </p>
    
</subsection>
<subsection name='Advanced Updaters'>
    <p>
Betwixt by default uses the property write method for standard properties 
and matched stems for composite properties (for more details, see 
<a href="#Using adder methods for composite properties">here</a>) 
to update property values when reading beans. 
These approaches should be sufficient for most cases. 
But this can be overruled on a per element basis.
    </p>
    <p>
By using a .betwixt file, the method used to update the bean can be controlled on a per element basis.
When the value of the <code>updater</code> attribute of an <code>&lt;element&gt;</code> element is set,
Betwixt will try to find a bean method with a matching name which takes a single parameter.
When such a matching method exists, this will be called to update the property value.
    </p>
    <p>
For example, the following betwixt file fragment: 
    
<source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<info primitiveTypes="element">
  <element name="bean">
        ...
        <element name='name' property='name' updater='nameSetter'/>
        ...
  </element>
</info>
]]></source>

will look for a method called 'nameSetter' and use that to update the value mapped to the 'name' element.
    </p>
</subsection>
</section>

    <section name='Reading Beans - In Depth'>
    
        <subsection name='Understanding The Class Creation Chain'>
            <p>
Betwixt uses the <em>Chain Of Responsibility</em> pattern to decide the object which should be created 
for a particular element. The standard chain contains <code>ChainedBeanCreator</code>s which implement
functionality such as standard bean creation based on the expected type and the returning of beans by ID.
This allows users to easily insert their own <code>ChainedBeanCreator</code>s into the chain - or to 
replace the standard Betwixt chain completely.
        </p>
    </subsection>
    
        <subsection name='Customizing Bean Creation'>
            <p>
The chain used by the BeanReader is part of the <code>ReadConfiguration</code> and is accessed via the 
BeanCreationChain property. For example the following sets a custom chain.
<source><![CDATA[
        BeanCreationChain chain = MyBeanCreationChain();
        BeanReader reader = new BeanReader();
        ...
        reader.registerBeanClass("bean", Bean.class);
        reader.getReadConfiguration().setBeanCreationChain(chain);
        ...
        Bean bean = (Bean) reader.parse(in);
        ...
]]></source>
        </p>
            <p>
Betwixt provides a standard (list-backed) chain called BeanCreationList. This provides an easy methods to 
register your own <code>ChainedBeanCreator</code>. It also provides a factory method which creates an instance
with the standard betwixt chain already set. For example, the following inserts a custom in second place:
<source><![CDATA[
        BeanCreationList chain = BeanCreationList.createStandardChain();
        BeanCreator creator = MyBeanCreator();
        chain.insertBeanCreator(1, creator);
]]></source>
        </p>
            <p>
Another useful class is <code>ChainedBeanCreationFactory</code>. This contains factory methods for the 
<code>BeanCreator</code>s used by Betwixt. This allows a user to easily mix custom and standard creators.
        </p>
    </subsection>
    
        <subsection name='Example: Enums'>
            <p>
Herein is contained a practical example demonstrating how custom bean creation may be used.
        </p>
            <p>
A common java pattern is the use of strongly typed Enum classes. Let's say that you have the following class:
<source><![CDATA[
public class CompassPoint {

    public static final CompassPoint NORTH = new CompassPoint("North");
    public static final CompassPoint SOUTH = new CompassPoint("South");
    public static final CompassPoint EAST = new CompassPoint("East");
    public static final CompassPoint WEST = new CompassPoint("West");
    
    private String name;
    
    private CompassPoint(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }
    
    public String getName() {
        return name;
    }
}
]]></source>
and you have a bean which you would like to map to xml and back using Betwixt. Betwixt is bean-centric. 
It aims to make mapping beans easy. But, <code>CompassPoint</code> objects are not beans and do not
have the empty constructors that Betwixt requires.
        </p>
            <p>
A good way to solve this problem is to create a custom BeanCreator which knows how to create an enum
of the right type from the 'name' attribute value. For example:
<source><![CDATA[
public class CompassPointEnumCreator implements ChainedBeanCreator {
    public Object create(ElementMapping mapping, ReadContext context, BeanCreationChain chain) {
        if (CompassPoint.class.equals(mapping.getType())) {
            String value = mapping.getAttributes().getValue("name");
            if ("North".equals(value)) {
                return CompassPoint.NORTH;
            }
            if ("South".equals(value)) {
                return CompassPoint.SOUTH;
            }
            if ("East".equals(value)) {
                return CompassPoint.EAST;
            }
            if ("West".equals(value)) {
                return CompassPoint.WEST;
            }
        }
        return chain.create(mapping, context);
    }
}
]]></source>
        </p>
            <p>
Once this class has been created, all that remains is to add this into the chain. In this case,
it's probably most convenient to use the factory method to create a standard chain and then insert
the BeanCreator at a suitable position:
<source><![CDATA[
    BeanCreationList chain = BeanCreationList.createStandardChain();
    chain.insertBeanCreator(1, new EnumCreator());
    ...
    BeanReader reader = new BeanReader();
    reader.getXMLIntrospector().setAttributesForPrimitives(true);
    reader.getXMLIntrospector().setWrapCollectionsInElement(false);
    reader.getReadConfiguration().setBeanCreationChain(chain);
    ...
]]></source>
Now you're ready to start reading enums!
        </p>
    </subsection>
    
        <subsection name='Using Bean Includes'>
            <p>
<code>IncludeBeanCreator</code> is a <code>ChainedBeanCreator</code> that implements a system
of 'includes' files. Adding this class to the bean creation chain will load and read the file
specified by the <code>include-file</code> attribute whenever it is encountered.
The file will be loaded as a resource by the current <code>ClassLoader</code> using the standard rules.
        </p>
            <p>
A similar effect could be accumplished through the using of xml entity's.
There are occasions when this is inconvenient and so it's useful to have an alternative
available.
        </p>
    </subsection>
    	<subsection name='Reading Polymorphic Mappings'>
    		<p>
A polymophic mapping is one where the decision about the element type and name
is postponed from introspection time to bind time. This allows reading of
collections containing mixed types distinguished by element name. For example:
		</p>    		
<source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<container>
  <elementA/>
  <elementB/>
</container>
]]></source>
			<p>
Polymorphic mappings should be set up using dot betwixt files. 
The name attribute for the element should be omitted
and mappings registered for the contained object types.
It is usually more convenient to use a single file containing all the mappings.
For example:
		</p>
<source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<betwixt-config>
  <class name='SomeContainer'>
    <element name='container'>
      <!-- Polymorphic so no name attribute -->
      <element property='element'/>
    </element>
  </class>
  <!-- Need to register mappings for types of contained elements 
       (when Betwixt default strategy is used) -->
  <class name='ContainedElementA'>
    <element name='elementA'/>
  </class>
  <class name='ContainedElementB'>
    <element name='elementB'/>
  </class>
</betwixt-config>
]]></source>
			<p>
By default, in this circumstance Betwixt will try to guess the correct resolution
by searching all registered <code>XMLBeanInfo</code>'s for an appropriate match.
If more thn one is found, an arbitrary one is used. 
In many cases, this accords well with intuition. There are
occasions when more finely grained control may be required. The resolution is
therefore factored into <code>PolymorphicReferenceResolver</code> 
(a pluggable strategy) on <code>XMLIntrospector</code>. 
A custom resolver allows alternative algorithms for determining
type to be used which can (for example) ignore the mappings registered.
Note that the default implementation is provided by the default
<code>XMLBeanInfoRegistry</code> implementation.
Therefore, when using a custom registry a custom resolver must also
be used.
		</p>
    </subsection>
</section>

</body>
</document>
