<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
   or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
   distributed with this work for additional information
   regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
   to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
   "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
   with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
   software distributed under the License is distributed on an
   "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
   KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
   specific language governing permissions and limitations
   under the License.  
-->
<document>
   <properties>
      <title>Design</title>
      <author email="rdonkin@apache.org">Robert Burrell Donkin</author>
   </properties>

   <body>
      <section name="Design Changes">
         <subsection name='Primitives'>
            <p>
               Betwixt used to analyse the bound class type at mapping time.
               Those regarded as primitives were recognized and a different
               mapping algorithm used.
            </p>
            <p>
               This is inefficient and also leads to greater complexity in the
               mapping algorithm. Primitives should be recognized at introspection
               time and the Descriptors produced should reflect these changes.
            </p>
            <p>
               The first work should be to change how the primitive mapping to
               elements works. The introspector should recognize primitives
               at Introspection time and create an appropriate ElementDescriptor
               containing a TextDescriptor with an appropriate Updator.
               This updator should be called in the same way as any other.
            </p>
         </subsection>
         <subsection name='Mapping Collectives'>
            <p>
               This means mapping such collectives as Maps and Collections.
            </p>
            <p>
               Previously, this has been done through special algorithms at
               binding time.
            </p>
            <p>
               In particular, the isWrapCollectionsInElement needs to be
               decrepated and all calls removed.
            </p>
         </subsection>
         <subsection name='Hollow Elements'>
            <p>
               A hollow element is an element which is one that is mapped
               to the root of a newly bean instance. A hollow element may
               correspond to a singular or collective property.
            </p>
         </subsection>
         <subsection name='Frame Element'>
            <p>
               A frame element is present in the xml and is unbound to any
            </p>
         </subsection>
      </section>
   </body>
</document>

