<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Betwixt - Turning beans into XML</title>
  <author email="jstrachan@apache.org">James Strachan</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="Commons Betwixt : Turning beans into XML">


<p>
   The Betwixt library provides an XML introspection mechanism
   for mapping beans to XML in a flexible way. It is implemented using an 
   XMLIntrospector and XMLBeanInfo classes which are similar to the standard 
   Introspector and BeanInfo from the Java Beans specification.</p>
<p>
   Betwixt provides a way of turning beans into XML as well as automatically 
   generating digester rules in a way that can be customized on a per type 
   manner in the same way that the BeanInfo mechanism can be used to customize 
   the default introspection on a java object.</p>

</section>

<section name="Releases">

  <subsection name='Betwixt 0.8'>
    <p>
Betwixt 0.8 is a feature release.
Improvements have been made to suppression strategies.
Enhancements have been made to mapping formats.
Mixed collections are now handled more completely.
For full details see the <a href='http://commons.apache.org/betwixt/betwixt-0.8/RELEASE-NOTES.txt'>release notes</a>
and <a href='http://commons.apache.org/betwixt/betwixt-0.8/docs/index.html'>release documentation</a>. 
	</p>
    <p>
Betwixt 0.8 is 
<a href='http://commons.apache.org/betwixt/download_betwixt.cgi'>available</a>
in binary and source distributions.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name='Betwixt 0.7'>
    <p>
Betwixt 0.7 is a feature release. 
A number of new strategies have been introduced to add flexibility. Improvements
have been made to binding and introspection including improved support for polymophism.
Improvements have been made to the dot betwixt file format including support
for multiple specifications within the same file. 
For full details see the <a href='tasks.html#Completed'>tasks documentation</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
Betwixt 0.7 is binary compatible with 0.6 but a number of changes have been
made to some semantics. It is believed that the impact of these changes
should be minimal. Details (together with some ways to mitigate) can be found on the 
 <a href='tasks.html#Semantic%20Changes'>list of semantic incompatibilities</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
This release is binary compatible with the 0.6 codebase but the methods deprecated
in 0.6 (and earlier) are likely to be removed soon.
    </p>
    <p>
Betwixt 0.7 is 
<a href='http://commons.apache.org/betwixt/download_betwixt.cgi'>available</a>
in binary and source distributions.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name='Betwixt 0.6'>
    <p>
Betwixt release 0.6 is the first release containing the refactored codebase 
featuring an improved design. This is a service release for those who have been
using the code from the CVS branch and offers an easy, compatible upgrade path
for those using the 0.5 design. It is recommended that all users should upgrade
to this release since the 0.5 design is no longer actively supported and is 
limited in terms of functionality. 
    </p>
    <p>
This release is binary compatible with the 0.5 codebase but the methods deprecated
in 0.5 are likely to be removed soon after 0.6 is released.
    </p>
    <p>
Betwixt 0.6 is available in 
<a href='http://commons.apache.org/betwixt/download_betwixt.cgi'>available</a>
in binary and source distributions.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Betwixt 0.5">
    <p>
Betwixt release 0.5 is intended to consolidate the codebase released as 1.0 Alpha 1. 
It is a service release for those users who want or need an official release of this 
codebase. This numbering system more accurately reflects the current state of the codebase 
- stable, mature but limited with APIs that may be subject to change in future releases. 
It is unlikely that active ASF development will continue for this released codebase 
since further development efforts are already focussed on newer designs.
    </p>
    <p>
The current CVS HEAD code now contains the merged refactoring branch. A 
baseline 0.6 release is planned for this code once 0.5 has been released.
    </p>
    <p>
For more information, see the road map <a href='http://wiki.apache.org/commons/Betwixt'>
on the wiki</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
Betwixt 0.5 is 
<a href='http://commons.apache.org/betwixt/download_betwixt.cgi'>available</a>
in binary and source distributions.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection name="Betwixt 1.0 Alpha 1">
    <p>
    <strong>Betwixt 1.0 Alpha 1</strong> - 28 Jan 2003
    </p>
    <p>
Betwixt 1.0 Alpha 1 is 
<a href='http://commons.apache.org/betwixt/download_betwixt.cgi'>available</a>
in binary and source distributions.
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>
<section name="Nightly Builds">
    <p>
        Nightly builds are built once a day from the current HEAD.
        This is (nearly) the lastest code and so should be treated with caution!
    </p>
    <p>
        You can get the nightly builds from 
        <a href="http://people.apache.org/builds/commons/nightly/commons-betwixt/">here</a>
    </p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
