<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Betwixt FAQ</title>
    <author email="jstrachan@apache.org">James Strachan</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Frequently Asked Questions">
    <p>
      This document attempts to answer some of the more frequently asked
      questions regarding various aspects of Betwixt.  These questions are
      typically asked over and over again on the mailing lists, as a
      courtesy to the developers, we ask that you read this document
      before posting to the mailing lists.  
    </p>
    <p><strong>General</strong></p>
    <ol>
      <li>
        <a href="#what-is-betwixt">
          What is Betwixt?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#why-called-betwixt">
          Why is this called Betwixt?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#comparison">
          How does Betwixt compare to technologies like JAXB and Castor?
        </a>
      </li>
    </ol>
    <p><strong>Building Betwixt</strong></p>
    <ol>
      <li>
        <a href="#how-to-build">
          How do I build Betwixt?
        </a>
      </li>
    </ol>

    <section name="General">
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="what-is-betwixt">
            What is Betwixt?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          The Betwixt library provides an XML introspection mechanism
   		  for mapping beans to XML in a flexible way.
          Please see the <a href="index.html">Home page</a> and <a
          href="overview.html">Overview</a> documents for more detail.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="why-called-betwixt">
          	Why is this called Betwixt?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          I grepped a dictionary for words containing B*T*X for Bean To XML.
          There's not many words around containing those 3 letters in order. 
		  Betwixt also seems a fitting name as its the stuff between (betwixt) Beans and XML.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="comparison">
          	How does Betwixt compare to technologies like JAXB and Castor?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
			Where JAXP and Castor are strong is when you have a well agreed schema (XML
			Schema for Castor or a DTD in the case of JAXB, last time I looked) and want
			to auto-generate beans for parsing and processing the XML.
        </dd>
        <dd>
			Betwixt is strong is when you've already got the beans and just want a nice
			looking XML format to serialize/deserialize your beans. 
			Indeed with Betwixt you can just write your beans and not even worry
			about XML schemas and providing you follow a simple bean naming convention
			(the use of getter, setter and <i>adder</i> methods) you'll get nice looking XML for free.
        </dd>
        <dd>
			In JDK1.4 there is a 
			<a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/docs/guide/beans/changes14.html">long term bean serialization</a> 
			mechanism which you can use. However Betwixt generates cleaner looking XML which can be customized
			to your own look and feel. Long term bean serialization doesn't generate nice looking XML.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      
    </section>
    <section name="Building Betwixt">
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="how-to-build">
            How do I build Betwixt?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          Betwixt uses Maven for its build system. So you should be able to build Betwixt just like
          any other Maven enabled project. Please see the 
          <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/maven/start/index.html">Maven</a> 
          documentation for details.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
