<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Betwixt FAQ</title>
    <author email="jstrachan@apache.org">James Strachan</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Frequently Asked Questions">
    <p>
      This document attempts to answer some of the more frequently asked
      questions regarding various aspects of Betwixt.  These questions are
      typically asked over and over again on the mailing lists, as a
      courtesy to the developers, we ask that you read this document
      before posting to the mailing lists.  
    </p>
    <p><strong>General</strong></p>
    <ol>
      <li>
        <a href="#what-is-betwixt">
          What is Betwixt?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#why-called-betwixt">
          Why is this called Betwixt?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#comparison">
          How does Betwixt compare to technologies like JAXB and Castor?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#performance">
          Why Can I Make Betwixt Bind Faster?
        </a>
      </li>
    </ol>
    <p><strong>Writing Beans</strong></p>
    <ol>
      <li>
        <a href="#output-options">
          In what forms can Betwixt output the xml?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#pretty-print">
          Can <code>BeanWriter</code> produce xml that's easy (for a human ;) to read?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#cycles">
          How does Betwixt cope with beans which have cyclic reference graphs?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#stop-generating-ids">
          How can I stop Betwixt generating <code>ID</code> attribute values for my beans?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#empty-elements">
          How can I stop Betwixt write out empty elements?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#cdata">
          How can I stop Betwixt escaping my character data?
        </a>
      </li>            
    </ol>
    <p><strong>Reading Beans</strong></p>
    <ol>
      <li>
        <a href="#digester-limitation">
          How can I make my extra digestion <em>Rule</em>s work with Betwixt?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#bean-read-failure">
          Why does reading my xml return null?
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
      	<a href="#betwixt-matching-adders">
How can I make Betwixt match adders to collective properties when using
a <code>.betwixt</code> file <em>without</em> also adding default propertes?
      	</a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="#read-validation">
          Does Betwixt Validate Values Read?
        </a>
      </li>
    </ol>
    <p><strong>Building Betwixt</strong></p>
    <ol>
      <li>
        <a href="#how-to-build">
          How do I build Betwixt?
        </a>
      </li>
    </ol>

    <subsection name="General">
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="what-is-betwixt">
            What is Betwixt?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          The Betwixt library provides an XML introspection mechanism
   		  for mapping beans to XML in a flexible way.
          Please see the <a href="index.html">Home page</a> and <a
          href="guide/start.html">Guide</a> documents for more detail.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="why-called-betwixt">
          	Why is this called Betwixt?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          I grepped a dictionary for words containing B*T*X for Bean To XML.
          There's not many words around containing those 3 letters in order. 
		  Betwixt also seems a fitting name as its the stuff between (betwixt) Beans and XML.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="comparison">
          	How does Betwixt compare to technologies like JAXB and Castor?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
			Where JAXP and Castor are strong is when you have a well agreed schema (XML
			Schema for Castor or a DTD in the case of JAXB, last time I looked) and want
			to auto-generate beans for parsing and processing the XML.
        </dd>
        <dd>
			Betwixt is strong is when you've already got the beans and just want a nice
			looking XML format to serialize/deserialize your beans. 
			Indeed with Betwixt you can just write your beans and not even worry
			about XML schemas and providing you follow a simple bean naming convention
			(the use of getter, setter and <i>adder</i> methods) you'll get nice looking XML for free.
        </dd>
        <dd>
			In JDK1.4 there is a 
			<a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/docs/guide/beans/changes14.html">long term bean serialization</a> 
			mechanism which you can use. However Betwixt generates cleaner looking XML which can be customized
			to your own look and feel. Long term bean serialization doesn't generate nice looking XML.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="performance">
          	Why Can I Make Betwixt Faster?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
Betwixt is a dynamic binder. This means that it uses reflection. One of the biggest costs
is introspection by reflection of the beans. Betwixt caches the results of reflection in a
<code>XMLBeanInfoRegistry</code> implementation. One simple way to improve performance is to
share a single, threadsafe implementation (<code>DefaultXMLBeanInfoRegistry</code>, for example) 
between all readers and writers.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Writing Beans">     
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="output-options">
          	In what forms can Betwixt output the xml?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
            Betwixt can output xml as streaming text or as SAX events.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="pretty-print">
          	Can <code>BeanWriter</code> produce xml that's easy (for a human ;) to read?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
            Yes! Call
<source>
beanWriter.enablePrettyPrint();
</source>
            (For those who are extra picky, how this is done can also be adjusted.
            See java docs for details.)
        </dd>
      </dl>      
      
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="cycles">
          	How does Betwixt cope with beans which have cyclic reference graphs?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
            The default behaviour is to use the <code>ID</code>-<code>IDREF</code> mechanism
            (described in the xml specification). Betwixt will automatically assign <code>ID</code>
            values to beans as it write out the graph. If it comes to a bean that it's written
            before, it will write an <code>IDREF</code> value matching the original.
        </dd>
      </dl>  
      
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="stop-generating-ids">
          	How can I stop Betwixt generating <code>ID</code> attribute values for my beans?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
            This is controlled by a property on <code>BeanWriter</code>. Call
<source>
beanWriter.setWriteIDs(false);
</source>
            and then Betwixt will no longer automatically add <code>ID</code> attributes.
            Once this property is set (to false), when a cycle reference is encountered
            in the bean graph, a <code>CyclicReferenceException</code> will be thrown.
        </dd>
      </dl>   

      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="empty-elements">
          	How can I stop Betwixt writing out empty elements?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
            An empty element (for this discussion) is one which has no attributes and no
            child elements which are not empty. 
            If you want to stop Betwixt writing out empty elements, then call:
<source>
beanWriter.setWriteEmptyElements(false);
</source>
            (before writing your bean).
        </dd>
      </dl>   

      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="cdata">
          	How can I stop Betwixt escaping my character data?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
Betwixt processes the character data so that valid xml is created.
The detault is to escape all character data but this can be changed
by plugging in a new <a href='guide/output.html#Content%20Encoding'>mixed context 
encoding strategy</a>.
        </dd>
      </dl> 
          
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Reading Beans">
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="digester-limitation">
            How can I make my extra digestion <em>Rule</em>s work with Betwixt?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
            Betwixt uses <a href='http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/digester/index.html'>Digester</a> for bean
            reading. With care and knowledge of the way that Betwixt reads beans,
            extra rules can be used to add custom functionality.
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <a name="bean-read-failure">
            Why does reading my xml return null?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
            Here are some common reasons why this may happen:
            <ul>
            <li><strong>The class lacks a no-argument construct.</strong>
            Betwixt only supports creation of beans with no-argument constructors.
            This may be fixed in a future release. (Patches for this gratefully received!)</li>
            <li><strong>The class need to be registered at a custom path.</strong>
            You may need to use <code>registerBeanRegister(String path, Class beanClass)</code>
            to register the class at a particular path.</li>
            </ul>
        </dd>
         <dt>
          <a name="betwixt-matching-adders">
How can I make Betwixt match adders to collective properties when using
a <code>.betwixt</code> file <em>without</em> also adding default propertes?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
Add the <code>&lt;addDefaults&gt;</code> and to it add an attribute 
<code>add-properties=&quot;false&quot;</code>.
        </dd>    
         <dt>
          <a name="read-validation">
Does Betwixt Validate Values Read?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
Betwixt does not directly validate any property values read. The convertion of the string
in the xml to values suitable for setting on the bean property is delegated to the 
ObjectStringConverter. The converter may - or may not - validate values (and throw exceptions 
when they fall outside acceptable ranges).
        </dd>       
      </dl>
      
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Building Betwixt">
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <a name="how-to-build">
            How do I build Betwixt?
          </a>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          Betwixt uses Maven for its build system. So you should be able to build Betwixt just like
          any other Maven enabled project. Please see the 
          <a href="http://maven.apache.org/maven-1.x/">Maven</a> 
          documentation for details.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </subsection>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
